

S  
 L I D E   P O S I T I O N S ,   H A R M O N I C S   &   S C A L E
video/tenortrombone1.flv
notes/tenortrombone1.swf
0
Performer: Bryan Heath
The trombone's slide distinguishes it from any other instrument. The slide provides 7 positions, a tritone's worth of fundamentals allowing for complete control over intonation and making glissandos of up to a tritone playable. 
Note that the distance between positions increases as more of the slide tubing is used.
20
Performer: Bryan Heath
The first order of pitch selection for all brass instruments is producing a partial from the harmonic series. When the tenor trombone is played with the slide in first position and no triggers invoked, the concert pitch of the fundamental is the B-flat below the bass clef, an octave lower than the B-flat trumpet's fundamental. 
Note that the partials are successively closer together, and that the 7th partial is "out of tune."
41
As the slide provides different fundamentals, seven arrays of harmonic series partials are available. These arpeggios range from the 2nd to the 6th partial in the seven slide positions.
59
Predicting the slide position for a note is a simple matter of observing that note's position in the arrays in the line above. 
Here the F trigger (which is demonstrated on the following page) is used to play the low F and C in first position. Without the trigger these pitches would have to be played in VI position. When the trigger is used no slide position greater than IV is needed to play this entire scale.
66
Predicting the slide position for a note is a simple matter of observing that note's position in the arrays in the line above. 
From this A upward, all the pitches are playable in I, II, or III position, and are playable in at least 2 different positions.
71
Predicting the slide position for a note is a simple matter of observing that note's position in the arrays in the line above.
The highest three notes shown here are played using the 9th and 10th partials, and can be difficult to attack accurately on the tenor trombone. Many late 18th- and early 19th-century 1st trombone parts were composed for alto trombone, a smaller instrument more reliable in this register.
78
Skips require non-adjacent partial selection by the embouchure. 
Here the skips are from the 3rd to 6th partial. 
84
Skips require non-adjacent partial selection by the embouchure. 
Here the skips are from the 6th to 3rd partial. Downward skips are slightly less immediate in their response. 



T  
 R I G G E R S   &   G L I S S A N D O S
video/tenortrombone2.flv
notes/tenortrombone2.swf
0
Pedal tones (fundamentals in the harmonic series) are very effective in the first three positions. Pedal tones lower than G can be problematic on a tenor trombone.
16
Almost all orchestral trombones now have at least one "attachment," extra tubing brought into play by a "trigger" operated by the left thumb. The common F attachment (or "F trigger") increases the tubing's total length by a third, so that the instrument's fundamental in first position is lowered to the F an octave below the bass clef. The pitches played here are 2nd partials (not pedal tones).
30
Since the trigger adds 33% to the length of the tubing, the slide has to move 33% farther to create a half-step, so only 6 slide positions are possible with the trigger engaged, covering a perfect 4th instead of a tritone. The F trigger fills in the gap between E (the non-trigger VII position 2nd partial) and pedal B-flat, EXCEPT for the B-natural.
The six trigger positions are numbered I through VII, with V omitted; this numbering allows the numbers for the positions to be close to where they would be without the trigger.
35
The trigger effectively doubles the number of harmonic series from which any pitch can be selected, making otherwise awkward passages easier and making allowing for trigger-trills. Triggers are most often used in the lowest register, where partials are further apart.
41
The trigger effectively doubles the number of harmonic series from which any pitch can be selected, making otherwise awkward passages easier and making allowing for trigger-trills. Triggers are most often used in the lowest register, where partials are further apart.
47
The F trigger is operated by the left-hand thumb. Here the same pitch is played as the 6th partial of the open B-flat trombone and as the 8th partial of the F fundamental created by the trigger. Note that the embouchure is set for the region of the pitch and does not need to adjust to the changing partial. The inertia of sound wave automatically "finds" that pitch. Articulation is created not by the tongue, but by a bump in the sound wave as it adjusts to the new partial/fundamental relationship.
56
These are the only tritone slide-glissandos available without using the trigger in the range employing the 2nd through 6th partials.  Of course, smaller interval slide-glissandos within the limits of these are possible.
71
Glissandos work equally well in either direction.
77
The trigger makes more slide-glissandos possible; note that the largest glissando interval possible while using the trigger is a perfect 4th. The third and fourth glissandos in this set are also available without the trigger (see previous line).



R  
 E G I S T E R   &   A R T I C U L A T I O N   C O L O R S
video/tenortrombone3.flv
notes/tenortrombone3.swf
0
The trombone is full, dark and rich in its lowest register. 
4
The trombone is full, dark and rich in its lowest register.
8
The trombone is full, dark and rich in its lowest register.
11
The trombone is full, dark and rich in its lowest register.		
15
The trombone's middle range is singing and clear, and very responsive to dynamic and articulation variation.
18
The trombone's middle range is singing and clear, and very responsive to dynamic and articulation variation.
21
The trombone's middle range is singing and clear, and very responsive to dynamic and articulation variation.
24
The trombone's middle range is singing and clear, and very responsive to dynamic and articulation variation.		
28
This middle high register is arguably the most powerful and characteristically colorful register of the tenor trombone. 
32
This middle high register is arguably the most powerful and characteristically colorful register of the tenor trombone.
35
This middle high register is arguably the most powerful and characteristically colorful register of the tenor trombone.
38
This middle high register is arguably the most powerful and characteristically colorful register of the tenor trombone.		
42
The high register can be brilliant and thrilling, and also sweet and nuanced. This phrase could be notated in any of the three clefs shown here, but tenor clef is most commonly used for this range.
45
The high register can be brilliant and thrilling, and also sweet and nuanced. This phrase could be notated in any of the three clefs shown here, but tenor clef is most commonly used for this range.
49
The high register can be brilliant and thrilling, and also sweet and nuanced. This phrase could be notated in any of the three clefs shown here, but tenor clef is most commonly used for this range.
52
The high register can be brilliant and thrilling, and also sweet and nuanced. This phrase could be notated in any of the three clefs shown here, but tenor clef is most commonly used for this range.		
56
Legato articulation is fundamentally different on the trombone from any other brass instrument since some degree of tonguing must be used to hide the movement of the slide between pitches (unless adjacent notes can be played as different partials in the same slide position). Amazing coordination is displayed in providing the illusion of a legato articulation as its heard on valve instruments.
62
The slur-two-tongue-two articulation so common and intuitively natural on other wind instruments must be imitated on the trombone with varying degrees of articulation, since many of the "slurred" the notes must be tongued because of slide movement.
68
Single tonguing is generally slower than the other articulation options demonstrated here, but is also the most deliberate and forceful.
74
Double-tonguing is very effective for fast passages on brass instruments, although the slide of the trombone does not naturally move as quickly as valves would allow.
76
Double-tonguing is very effective for fast passages on brass instruments, although the slide of the trombone does not naturally move as quickly as valves would allow.



M  
 O R E   A R T I C U L A T I O N S   &   V I B R A T O
video/tenortrombone4.flv 
notes/tenortrombone4.swf
0
Staccato articulation is effective in all registers of the trombone.
3
Staccato articulation is effective in all registers of the trombone.
7
Triple-tonguing can be very effective on all brass instruments. It must be remembered that when triple-tonguing skips (as in this example) the amount of preparation time moving into the new note is considerably shortened, making the attacks less secure.
11
Flutter-tonguing is effective throughout the range of the trombone.
17
A slight amount of vibrato is normal on the trumpet, applied according to the taste and discretion of the performer. Composers may specify varying amounts of vibrato.
24
A slight amount of vibrato is normal on the trumpet, applied according to the taste and discretion of the performer. Composers may specify varying amounts of vibrato.
32
A slight amount of vibrato is normal on the trumpet, applied according to the taste and discretion of the performer. Composers may specify varying amounts of vibrato. The slide makes possible a degree of vibrato not available on other wind instruments.



M  
 U T E S
video/tenortrombone5.flv 
notes/tenortrombone5.swf
0
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used.
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.
The distinct colors of the various mutes are more obvious at louder dynamic levels.
11
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used. 
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.
The distinct colors of the various mutes are more obvious at louder dynamic levels.
25
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used. 
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.
The distinct colors of the various mutes are more obvious at louder dynamic levels.
41
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used. 
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.
The three different positions for the stem of the harmon mute create very different timbres.
47
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used. 
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.
The three different positions for the stem of the harmon mute create very different timbres. The "wa-wa" effect is most pronounced with the harmon mute in "stem in" position.
60
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used. 
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.
The three different positions for the stem of the harmon mute create very different timbres. Note that "stem extended" and "stem removed" are preferable to the ambiguous "stem out."
66
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used. 
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.
The three different positions for the stem of the harmon mute create very different timbres. Note that "stem extended" and "stem removed" are preferable to the ambiguous "stem out."
72
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used. 
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.

84
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used. 
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.
A straight mute adds a nasal brightness to the sound, so that at a quiet dynamic a straight muted trombone may actually sound louder than the open trombone.
99
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used. 
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.
A cup mute effectively softens the timbre of the trombone when used in quiet passages.
115
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used. 
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.
The three different positions for the stem of the harmon mute create very different timbres.
122
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used. 
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.
The three different positions for the stem of the harmon mute create very different timbres. The "wa-wa" effect is most pronounced with the harmon mute in "stem in" position.
135
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used. 
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.
The three different positions for the stem of the harmon mute create very different timbres. Note that "stem extended" and "stem removed" are preferable to the ambiguous "stem out."
148
These examples demonstrate three of the most common trombone mutes. Mute changes should be specific in naming the mute to be used. 
PLEASE NOTE: A significant amount of time must be given for the player to place and remove mutes.
The three different positions for the stem of the harmon mute create very different timbres. Note that "stem extended" and "stem removed" are preferable to the ambiguous "stem out."
157
Writing "brassy" invites the player to add a metallic quality to the tone color. This is possible only at a loud dynamic level.



P  
 A S S A G E
video/tenortrombone6.flv 
notes/tenortrombone6.swf 
0
The "Tuba Mirum" from Mozart's Requiem, a lyric obbligato to a bass arioso, is the earliest famous trombone excerpt. It remains one of the best examples of cantabile trombone style. The use of the high singing register is particularly appropriate to the flowing legato line.
14
The "Tuba Mirum" from Mozart's Requiem, a lyric obbligato to a bass arioso, is the earliest famous trombone excerpt. It remains one of the best examples of cantabile trombone style. The use of the high singing register is particularly appropriate to the flowing legato line.
25
The "Tuba Mirum" from Mozart's Requiem, a lyric obbligato to a bass arioso, is the earliest famous trombone excerpt. It remains one of the best examples of cantabile trombone style. The use of the high singing register is particularly appropriate to the flowing legato line.
37
The "Tuba Mirum" from Mozart's Requiem, a lyric obbligato to a bass arioso, is the earliest famous trombone excerpt. It remains one of the best examples of cantabile trombone style. The use of the high singing register is particularly appropriate to the flowing legato line.




P  
 A S S A G E   II
video/tenortrombone7.flv 
notes/tenortrombone7.swf 
0
This passage from Wagner's "Ride of the Valkyries" allows the trombone to be heard at its most powerful and heroic throughout two octaves of its middle to high range.
5
This passage from Wagner's "Ride of the Valkyries" allows the trombone to be heard at its most powerful and heroic throughout two octaves of its middle to high range.
12
This passage from Wagner's "Ride of the Valkyries" allows the trombone to be heard at its most powerful and heroic throughout two octaves of its middle to high range.
19
This passage from Wagner's "Ride of the Valkyries" allows the trombone to be heard at its most powerful and heroic throughout two octaves of its middle to high range.
25
This passage from Wagner's "Ride of the Valkyries" allows the trombone to be heard at its most powerful and heroic throughout two octaves of its middle to high range.
32
This passage from Wagner's "Ride of the Valkyries" allows the trombone to be heard at its most powerful and heroic throughout two octaves of its middle to high range.

