H A R M O N I C   S E R I E S

0: Performer: Elizabeth Pfaffle \n\n" +
"The first order of pitch selection for all brass instruments is producing a partial from the harmonic series. \n\n" +
"  When the modern horn is played open (no keys or triggers depressed), the concert pitch of the fundamental is the F an octave below the bass clef. \n\n" +
"  The lowest playable partial is the 2nd partial. \n\n" +
"Note that the partials are successively closer together, and that the 7th and 11th partials are \"out of tune.\" ",
11: Performer: Elizabeth Pfaffle \n\n" +
"  The valves lower the pitch of the fundamental by adding tubing to the air column. \n\n" +
"  The horn uses rotary valves played by the left hand. \n\n" +
"The 2nd valve (middle finger) adds enough tubing to lower the fundamental a half-step. ",
  20: Performer: Elizabeth Pfaffle \n\n" +
"  The valves lower the pitch of the fundamental by adding tubing to the air column. \n\n" +
"The horn uses rotary valves played by the left hand. \n\n" +
"The 1st valve (index finger) adds enough tubing to lower the fundamental a whole-step.", 


SC A L E S ,  V A L U E S   &   T R I G G E R S</titletext>
		<thevideo>video/horn2. \n\n" +
" flv</thevideo>
		<notesmovie>notes/horn2. \n\n" +
" swf</notesmovie>
		<cuepointer>0: The 2nd valve (middle finger) adds enough tubing to lower the fundamental a half-step. \n\n" +
"  The 1st valve (index finger) adds enough tubing to lower the fundamental a whole-step. \n\n" +
"  The 3rd valve lowers the fundamental an additional minor 3rd. \n\n" +
"  This allows for a chromatic scale of seven different fundamentals, enough to fill in the perfect-5th gap between the 2nd and 3rd partials. ",
  11: The 2nd valve (middle finger) adds enough tubing to lower the fundamental a half-step. \n\n" +
"  The 1st valve (index finger) adds enough tubing to lower the fundamental a whole-step. \n\n" +
"  The 3rd valve lowers the fundamental an additional minor 3rd. \n\n" +
"  This allows for a chromatic scale of seven different fundamentals, enough to fill in the perfect 5th gap between the 2nd and 3rd partials. ",
  22: Advanced players use the double horn, two complete sets of horn tubing joined at the mouthpiece and the bell. \n\n" +
"  As an alternative to the \"F side,\" a trigger operated by the left thumb routes the air through the \"B-flat side,\" whose open fundamental is a perfect 4th higher. \n\n" +
"  
The shorter tubing of the B-flat side allows the fundamental to be played as a pedal tone. ",
  24: Advanced players use the double horn, two complete sets of horn tubing joined at the mouthpiece and the bell. \n\n" +
"  As an alternative to the \"F side,\" a trigger operated by the left thumb routes the air through the \"B-flat side,\" whose open fundamental is a perfect 4th higher. \n\n" +
"  
The shorter tubing of the B-flat side allows high notes to speak more consistently. ",
  27: Advanced players use the double horn, two complete sets of horn tubing joined at the mouthpiece and the bell. \n\n" +
"  As an alternative to the \"F side,\" a trigger operated by the left thumb routes the air through the \"B-flat side,\" whose open fundamental is a perfect 4th higher. \n\n" +
"  
The shorter tubing of the B-flat side allows high notes to speak more consistently. \n\n" +
"  
Note that the 8th partial on the B-flat side is the same pitch as the 12th partial on the F-side. \n\n" +
"  Lower partials are more reliable. \n\n" +
" </commentary>		
		<cuepointer>32: This range of the horn is solid and very flexible. ",
  38: As the horn ascends through the written treble staff, the tone becomes brighter and more heroic. \n\n" +
"  Note that the performer's thumb has engaged the trigger, utilizing the B-flat horn. \n\n" +
"  Fingering may be observed in relationship to the B-flat harmonic series. ",
  43: Notes at the very top of the horn's range may not be as robust as expected; players need to exercise some caution in this range. \n\n" +
" </commentary>		
		<cuepointer>48: Although the B-flat side of the horn is a smaller, higher horn than the F-side, it makes available low pitches that are not possible without a double horn. \n\n" +
"  Depending on the performer, 3 to 5 pedal tones are possible. \n\n" +
" </commentary>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<headerletter>S</headerletter>
		<titletext> K I P S   &   T R I L L S</titletext>
		<thevideo>video/horn3. \n\n" +
" flv</thevideo>
		<notesmovie>notes/horn3. \n\n" +
" swf</notesmovie>
		<cuepointer>0: Composers may ask the performer to use open horn to evoke the tuning of the natural horn. \n\n" +
"  
In this first version, the performer uses the trigger and first valve to provide a standard intonation concert E-flat. \n\n" +
"  </commentary>
		<cuepointer>5: Composers may ask the performer to use open horn to evoke the tuning of the natural horn. \n\n" +
"  
In this second version, the performer uses the open F horn, using the slightly flat 7th partial E-flat. ",
  11: The horn is capable of responding to leaps with surprising agility. \n\n" +
"  Intervals which are easier to hear are also easier to play. ",
  14: The horn is capable of responding to leaps with surprising agility. \n\n" +
"  Intervals which are easier to hear are also easier to play. ",
  18: As the pitches get higher, the partials are closer together and more fingerings are possible for any given pitch. \n\n" +
"  The change in color is slight, but it is interesting to hear the intonation variety and articulation created by the change of fundamentals (although in this performance these are slightly tongued). \n\n" +
"  Here concert D is played as the 12th partial of G, the 10th partial of B-flat, and the 16th partial of D. ",
  24: Half-step trills are effectively performed using the 2nd valve. ",
  28: Whole-step trills may be performed as lip trills in the higher range where adjacent whole-step partials can be found. \n\n" +
" </commentary>		
		<cuepointer>34: Tremolos generally require that the embouchure alternate partials. ",
  37: Tremolos generally require that the embouchure alternate partials. ",
  40: Tremolos generally require that the embouchure alternate partials. \n\n" +
"  This may also need to be coordinated with valve trill. \n\n" +
" </commentary>		
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<headerletter>R</headerletter>
		<titletext> E G I S T E R   C O L O R S</titletext>
		<thevideo>video/horn4. \n\n" +
" flv</thevideo>
		<notesmovie>notes/horn4. \n\n" +
" swf</notesmovie>
		<cuepointer>0: The low register of the horn provides an effective alternate bass color for the brass section. \n\n" +
"  However, this region is relatively dark and lacking in definition and projection. \n\n" +
"  
Note that it is recommended to always indicate that bass clef is in \"new notation,\" since there persists some ambiguity regarding whether in bass clef the concert pitch is a 5th below (\"new\") or a 4th above (traditional) the written pitch. \n\n" +
"  </commentary>
		<cuepointer>3: The low register of the horn provides an effective alternate bass color for the brass section. \n\n" +
"  However, this region is relatively dark and lacking in definition and projection. \n\n" +
"  
Note that it is recommended to always indicate that bass clef is in \"new notation,\" since there persists some ambiguity regarding whether in bass clef the concert pitch is a 5th below (\"new\") or a 4th above (traditional) the written pitch. \n\n" +
"  </commentary>
		<cuepointer>6: The low register of the horn provides an effective alternate bass color for the brass section. \n\n" +
"  However, this region is relatively dark and lacking in definition and projection. \n\n" +
"  
Note that it is recommended to always indicate that bass clef is in \"new notation,\" since there persists some ambiguity regarding whether in bass clef the concert pitch is a 5th below (\"new\") or a 4th above (traditional) the written pitch. \n\n" +
"  </commentary>
		<cuepointer>9: The low register of the horn provides an effective alternate bass color for the brass section. \n\n" +
"  However, this region is relatively dark and lacking in definition and projection. \n\n" +
"  
Note that it is recommended to always indicate that bass clef is in \"new notation,\" since there persists some ambiguity regarding whether in bass clef the concert pitch is a 5th below (\"new\") or a 4th above (traditional) the written pitch. \n\n" +
"  </commentary>
		<cuepointer>12: The low-middle register of the horn is warm and responsive. \n\n" +
" </commentary>

		<cuepointer>14: The low-middle register of the horn is warm and responsive. \n\n" +
" </commentary>

		<cuepointer>17: The low-middle register of the horn is warm and responsive. \n\n" +
" </commentary>

		<cuepointer>19: The low-middle register of the horn is warm and responsive. \n\n" +
" </commentary>

		<cuepointer>22: The high-middle register is relatively bright, and capable of great contrast. \n\n" +
" </commentary>

		<cuepointer>24: The high-middle register is relatively bright, and capable of great contrast. \n\n" +
" </commentary>

		<cuepointer>26: The high-middle register is relatively bright, and capable of great contrast. \n\n" +
" </commentary>

		<cuepointer>29: The high-middle register is relatively bright, and capable of great contrast. \n\n" +
" </commentary>

		<cuepointer>32: The high range of the horn can be brilliant, robust and heroic; it is also possible (but not easy) to play softly in this range. \n\n" +
"  </commentary>

		<cuepointer>35: The high range of the horn can be brilliant, robust and heroic; it is also possible (but not easy) to play softly in this range. \n\n" +
"  </commentary>

		<cuepointer>37: The high range of the horn can be brilliant, robust and heroic; it is also possible (but not easy) to play softly in this range. \n\n" +
"  </commentary>

		<cuepointer>40: The high range of the horn can be brilliant, robust and heroic; it is also possible (but not easy) to play softly in this range. \n\n" +
"  </commentary>

	</page>
	
	<page>
		<headerletter>P</headerletter>
		<titletext> A S S A G E S</titletext>
		<thevideo>video/horn5. \n\n" +
" flv</thevideo>
		<notesmovie>notes/horn5. \n\n" +
" swf</notesmovie>
		<cuepointer>0: This is the opening horn solo from Richard Strauss's \"Till Eulenspiegel. \n\n" +
" \" The wide range and mixed articulations give it a robust playfulness. \n\n" +
"  </commentary>
		<cuepointer>6: This is the opening horn solo from Richard Strauss's \"Till Eulenspiegel. \n\n" +
" \" The wide range and mixed articulations give it a robust playfulness. \n\n" +
" 
\"New\" bass clef notation is used here, but in Strauss's traditional score and part the bass clef notes are written an octave lower. \n\n" +
" </commentary>		
		<cuepointer>10: This passage is also from Strauss's \"Till Eulenspiegel. \n\n" +
" \" It is the first horn part of a section scored for 4 horns playing 4-note chords, sharing the same rhythm and contour. \n\n" +
"  It displays the effectiveness of fast passagework for the horn. ",
  15: This passage is also from Strauss's \"Till Eulenspiegel. \n\n" +
" \" It is the first horn part of a section scored for 4 horns playing 4-note chords, sharing the same rhythm and contour. \n\n" +
"  It displays the effectiveness of fast passagework for the horn. \n\n" +
" </commentary>		
		<cuepointer>20: This is the second phrase of the horn solo from the second movement of Tchaikovsky's Fifth Symphony. \n\n" +
"  In spite of its expansively lyrical shape, its written range lies entirely within the treble staff. \n\n" +
"  The variations of color, dynamics, and articulation that Tchaikovsky crafts into this solo are given an ideal register for assured projection. \n\n" +
" </commentary>
	</page>
	
		<page>
		<headerletter>A</headerletter>
		<titletext> R T I C U L A T I O N   C O L O R S</titletext>
		<thevideo>video/horn6. \n\n" +
" flv</thevideo>
		<notesmovie>notes/horn6. \n\n" +
" swf</notesmovie>
		<cuepointer>0: The precise, immediate changes in the length of the column of air created by the valve mechanism provide a basic clarity of articulation on brass instruments, even when played legato with no tonguing. ",
  7: Slur-two-tongue-two articulation is very common and effective on brass instruments. ",
  14: Single tonguing is generally slower than the other articulation options demonstrated here, but is also the most deliberate and forceful. ",
  21: Double-tonguing is very effective for fast passages on brass instruments. \n\n" +
" </commentary>
	</page>
	
		<page>
		<headerletter>T</headerletter>
		<titletext> O N G U I N G   &   V I B R A T O   C O L O R S</titletext>
		<thevideo>video/horn7. \n\n" +
" flv</thevideo>
		<notesmovie>notes/horn7. \n\n" +
" swf</notesmovie>
		<cuepointer>0: Staccato articulation is effective in all but the highest and lowest registers of the horn, although it projects most clearly in the middle-high register. ",
  4: Staccato articulation is effective in all but the highest and lowest registers of the horn, although it projects most clearly in the middle-high register. ",
  8: Triple-tonguing can be very effective on all brass instruments. \n\n" +
"  It must be remembered that when triple-tonguing skips (as in this example) the amount of preparation time moving into the new note is considerably shortened, making the attacks less secure. ",
  13: Flutter-tonguing is effective in the middle and middle-high range of all brass instruments. ",
  22: A slight amount of vibrato is normal on the horn, applied according to the taste and discretion of the performer. \n\n" +
"  Composers may specify varying amounts of vibrato. ",
  27: A slight amount of vibrato is normal on the horn, applied according to the taste and discretion of the performer. \n\n" +
"  Composers may specify varying amounts of vibrato. ",
  35: A slight amount of vibrato is normal on the horn, applied according to the taste and discretion of the performer. \n\n" +
"  Composers may specify varying amounts of vibrato. ",
  44: A small amount of pitch-bend can be created by the embouchure or the right hand in the bell. ",
  50: A small amount of pitch-bend can be created by the embouchure or the right hand in the bell. \n\n" +
" </commentary>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<headerletter>S</headerletter>
		<titletext> T O P P I N G   &   M U T I N G</titletext>
		<thevideo>video/horn8. \n\n" +
" flv</thevideo>
		<notesmovie>notes/horn8. \n\n" +
" swf</notesmovie>
		<cuepointer>0: Mute changes on the horn require less extra movement than on other brass, since the normal position for the horn employs the right hand in the bell. ",
  13: Mute changes on the horn require less extra movement than on other brass instruments, since the normal position for the horn employs the right hand in the bell. \n\n" +
"  
At louder dynamic levels, the straight mute actually brightens and intensifies the sound of the horn. \n\n" +
" 
Note: While it is recommended that the kind of mute be specified for trumpet and trombone, on other brass instruments (including the horn) \"muted\" unambiguously designates the straight mute. ",
  25: Mute changes on the horn require less extra movement than on other brass instruments, since the normal position for the horn employs the right hand in the bell. \n\n" +
"  
Hand-stopping, placing the right hand far into the bell (designated by \"+\", cancelled by \"o\"), can be employed instantaneously. \n\n" +
"  
Loud stopped horn is intense, but the timbre is hollower than the straight mute timbre. \n\n" +
"  Even when played as loudly as possible, stopped horn does not project well. \n\n" +
"  </commentary>
		<cuepointer>35: Mute changes on the horn require less extra movement than on other brass instruments, since the normal position for the horn employs the right hand in the bell. \n\n" +
"  
The stopping mute should imitate the sound of stopped horn faithfully, and may facilitate performance, particularly in the lower register, where hand-stopping can be ineffective. \n\n" +
"  </commentary>
		<cuepointer>42: Mute changes on the horn require less extra movement than on other brass instruments, since the normal position for the horn employs the right hand in the bell. \n\n" +
" 
The fingering for open horn is given here to allow for comparison with the fingering for stopped horn and echo horn, given below. \n\n" +
"  \"T\" indicates use of the trigger invoking the B-flat side of the horn. ",
  54: Mute changes on the horn require less extra movement than on other brass instruments, since the normal position for the horn employs the right hand in the bell. \n\n" +
" 
Quiet muted passages effectively give the impression of distance. ",
  67: Mute changes on the horn require less extra movement than on other brass instruments, since the normal position for the horn employs the right hand in the bell. \n\n" +
" 
Quiet stopped horn is less edgy than muted horn. \n\n" +
" 
The fingering here would produce pitches a half-step lower if the horn were not stopped. \n\n" +
"  Stopping raises the horn's pitch a half-step. \n\n" +
"  
Advanced hornists may use alternate fingerings to improve intonation. ",
  78: Mute changes on the horn require less extra movement than on other brass instruments, since the normal position for the horn employs the right hand in the bell. \n\n" +
" 
The stopping mute should imitate the sound of stopped horn faithfully. ",
  88: Mute changes on the horn require less extra movement than on other brass instruments, since the normal position for the horn employs the right hand in the bell. \n\n" +
" 
To execute \"echo horn\" the hand is placed far enough into the bell to lower the pitch a half-step (but not as far as for stopping, which shifts the pitch UP a half-step). \n\n" +
"  The fingering here would produce pitches a half-step higher on an open horn. \n\n" +
"  
Echo horn softens the tone color as well as the dynamic level. \n\n" +
"  </commentary>
		<cuepointer>98: Writing \"brassy\" invites the player to add a metallic quality to the tone color. \n\n" +
"  This is possible only at a loud dynamic level. \n\n" +
" \"Cuivre\" is the French word for \"brassy. \n\n" +
" \" It does NOT mean stopped, although loud stopped passages are occasionally marked \"cuivre\" as an additional indication of a forced quality to the sound. \n\n" +
" </commentary>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<headerletter>N</headerletter>
		<titletext> A T U R A L   H O R N</titletext>
		<thevideo>video/naturalhorn. \n\n" +
" flv</thevideo>
		<notesmovie>notes/naturalhorn. \n\n" +
" swf</notesmovie>
		<cuepointer>0: The natural horn is the valveless forefather of the modern valved horn. \n\n" +
"  The fundamental can be changed by employing interchangeable crooks of various lengths. \n\n" +
"  Once the horn has been thus placed in its \"key,\" the only pitches available are those of its harmonic series, although intonation may be adjusted by the right hand placement. \n\n" +
" 
Baroque tuning is approximately a half-step lower than modern concert pitch; the concert pitch the fundamental here is the E an octave below the bass clef. ",
  3: The F and B are not available as natural partials. \n\n" +
"  F may be played as a sharp E, by \"stopping\" the horn with the right hand in the bell. \n\n" +
"  \"A\" may be played as a flat B-flat by removing the hand from the bell. \n\n" +
"  (this 14th partial is an octave higher than the 7th partial, which is already a bit flat. \n\n" +
" )</commentary>
		<cuepointer>10: The F and B are not available as natural partials. \n\n" +
"  F may be played as a sharp E, by \"stopping\" the horn with the right hand in the bell. \n\n" +
"  \"A\" may be played as a flat B-flat by removing the hand from the bell. \n\n" +
"  (this 14th partial is an octave higher than the 7th partial, which is already a bit flat. \n\n" +
" )</commentary>
		<cuepointer>14: This passage from Handel's \"Water Music\" is in Baroque F major, so the concert pitch is E major, a minor 6th lower than written. \n\n" +
"  The partials used and tuning adjustments are given above the staff. ",
  18: This passage from Handel's \"Water Music\" is in Baroque F major, so the concert pitch is E major, a minor 6th lower than written. \n\n" +
"  The partials used and tuning adjustments are given above the staff. ",
  22: This passage from Handel's \"Water Music\" is in Baroque F major, so the concert pitch is E major, a minor 6th lower than written. \n\n" +
"  The partials used and tuning adjustments are given above the staff. ",
  26: This passage from Handel's \"Water Music\" is in Baroque F major, so the concert pitch is E major, a minor 6th lower than written. \n\n" +
"  The partials used and tuning adjustments are given above the staff. \n\n" +
" </commentary>
	</page>
	
    <page>
		<headerletter>B</headerletter>  
		<titletext> A R O Q U E   H O R N</titletext>
		<thevideo>video/baroquehorn. \n\n" +
" flv</thevideo>
		<notesmovie>notes/baroquehorn. \n\n" +
" swf</notesmovie>
		<cuepointer>0: Another approach to adding extra pitches to the valveless harmonic series can be seen in the \"Baroque horn. \n\n" +
" \" Here a vent covered by the right hand thumb can be opened to raise the tuning a perfect 4th (similar to the \"B-flat side\" of the modern double horn). \n\n" +
"  A second vent covered by the left thumb raises the tuning a tritone (not used in this example). \n\n" +
" 
Here is the same \"Water Music\" example heard on the natural horn page. \n\n" +
"  When the vent is open, B-flat partials are used. ",
  6: Another approach to adding extra pitches to the valveless harmonic series can be seen in the \"Baroque horn. \n\n" +
" \" Here a vent covered by the right hand thumb can be opened to raise the tuning a perfect 4th (similar to the \"B-flat side\" of the modern double horn). \n\n" +
"  A second vent covered by the left thumb raises the tuning a tritone (not used in this example). \n\n" +
" 
Here is the same \"Water Music\" example heard on the natural horn page. \n\n" +
"  When the vent is open, B-flat partials are used. ",
  10: Another approach to adding extra pitches to the valveless harmonic series can be seen in the \"Baroque horn. \n\n" +
" \" Here a vent covered by the right hand thumb can be opened to raise the tuning a perfect 4th (similar to the \"B-flat side\" of the modern double horn). \n\n" +
"  A second vent covered by the left thumb raises the tuning a tritone (not used in this example). \n\n" +
" 
Here is the same \"Water Music\" example heard on the natural horn page. \n\n" +
"  When the vent is open, B-flat partials are used. ",
  14: Another approach to adding extra pitches to the valveless harmonic series can be seen in the \"Baroque horn. \n\n" +
" \" Here a vent covered by the right hand thumb can be opened to raise the tuning a perfect 4th (similar to the \"B-flat side\" of the modern double horn). \n\n" +
"  A second vent covered by the left thumb raises the tuning a tritone (not used in this example). \n\n" +
" 
Here is the same \"Water Music\" example heard on the natural horn page. \n\n" +
"  When the vent is open, B-flat partials are used. \n\n" +
" </commentary>
	</page>
		
</instrument>