

S  
 N A R E   &   B A S S   D R U M
video/drums1.flv
notes/drums1.swf
0
Performer: Eric Guinivan
The snare drum is almost always played with snare drum sticks, and usually the snares are on. Strokes can be broadened or accentuated by a flam (2 strokes total including the main note), a drag (3 strokes) or a ruff (4 or 5 strokes). These are played \"closed\" (rebounding strokes) when marked with a slur. These grace notes and rolls (which are normally also \"closed\") can also be played \"open\" with separate single strokes for a more deliberate effect. The final note is a rim-shot.
7
Performer: Eric Guinivan
The snare drum is almost always played with snare drum sticks, and usually the snares are on. Strokes can be broadened or accentuated by a flam (2 strokes total including the main note), a drag (3 strokes) or a ruff (4 or 5 strokes). These are played \"closed\" (rebounding strokes) when marked with a slur. These grace notes and rolls (which are normally also \"closed\") can also be played \"open\" with separate single strokes for a more deliberate effect. The final note is a rim-shot.
16
The snares my be turned off to create a clearer, deeper sound.
23
The snares my be turned off to create a clearer, deeper sound.
33
Bass drums may be positioned vertically, horizontally, or at an angle as in this demonstration. Bass drum beaters are specifically created for that particular instrument. Heavy felt beaters will provide the fullest, deepest sound.
45
Bass drums may be positioned vertically, horizontally, or at an angle as in this demonstration. Bass drum beaters are specifically created for that particular instrument. Heavy felt beaters will provide the fullest, deepest sound.
The quality of the bass drum can be changed significant by different degrees of left hand muting.
57
As beaters get harder, they generally have smaller mallet heads, increasing the contrast towards a more incisive, less rounded sound.
68
As beaters get harder, they generally have smaller mallet heads, increasing the contrast towards a more incisive, less rounded sound.
79
The bass drum is capable of a very large dynamic range.
99
When played with hard beaters, the bass drum can clearly articulate relatively fast rhythms.
106
The bass drum can be damped with the knee to create a very crisp articulation.
114
The bass drum is usually struck midway between the center of the drum and the edge. Varying this beating point creates an interesting variety of colors.



B  
 O N G O S ,  T I M B A L E S ,  T O M S   &   C O N G A
video/drums2.flv
notes/drums2.swf
0
Bongos always come in pairs and are the highest members of the drum family. They are traditionally played with the hands, but respond well to various kinds mallet (as demonstrated on the following page).
5
Bongos always come in pairs and are the highest members of the drum family. They are traditionally played with the hands, but respond well to various kinds mallet (as demonstrated on the following page).
10
Timbales are generally pitched between bongos and tomtoms. Their shell is shallower than tomtoms, and the sound is correspondingly bright and piercing.
15
Tomtom shells are deeper than timbales, and the sound deeper and more resonant. Tomtoms are available in a great variety of sizes. They are very responsive to the varieties of timbres created by different mallets.
24
The conga drum is traditionally played with the hands, using techniques that exploit the different timbres created by playing on different parts of the drum-head.
31
The conga drum is traditionally played with the hands, using techniques that exploit the different timbres created by playing on different parts of the drum-head.
41
A conga drum can also be played with various kinds of mallets, provide a sound that is relatively deep but still dry and precise. In this mode, it clearly projects over a large dynamic range.
47
A conga drum can also be played with various kinds of mallets, provide a sound that is relatively deep but still dry and precise. In this mode, it clearly projects over a large dynamic range.



D  
 R U M   M U L T I - S E T
video/drums3.flv
notes/drums3.swf
0
Drums are frequently arrayed together in a configuration chosen by the composer. This particular multi-set allows for a large range and four distinct basic drum colors, which are in turn varied on a large scale by the choice of mallets. 
The fatter sound of the handles of wood sticks, which are broader and heavier compared with the tips, provides a commonly used all-purpose wood-stick character for the multi-set. 
4
Drums are frequently arrayed together in a configuration chosen by the composer. This particular multi-set allows for a large range and four distinct basic drum colors, which are in turn varied on a large scale by the choice of mallets. 
The fatter sound of the handles of wood sticks, which are broader and heavier compared with the tips, provides a commonly used all-purpose wood-stick character for the multi-set. 
9
The pitch range of the drum multi-set is evident even when playing on the rims of the drums.
13
The pitch range of the drum multi-set is evident even when playing on the rims of the drums. 
17
Medium yarn mallets project a full-bodied sound throughout the multi-set.
20
Medium yarn mallets project a full-bodied sound throughout the multi-set.
26
Playing with the hands (actually the finger-tips) can produce warm, intimate but clear sound on all drums.
29
Playing with the hands (actually the finger-tips) can produce warm, intimate but clear sound on all drums.



T  
 A M B O U R I N E
video/drums4.flv 
notes/drums4.swf
0
The tambourine is actually two instruments in one -- a percussive hand drum, and a ringing metal shaker.
9
Relatively fast rhythms can be played on the tambourine by alternating knee and hand strokes.
14
The tambourine can be played with a delicate, sightly muted effect while resting on the knee.



D  
 R U M S E T  -  R O C K
video/drums5.flv 
notes/drums5.swf
0
The notational practice shown here is one that has become somewhat standard for drumset. Those instruments controlled by the foot are notated stems down. All the other activity is combined into one composite rhythm with the stems up. It is useful to give a staff key before the actual music, and also to indicate the name of an instrument as it enters. 
This first passage is a composed excerpt, imitating a rock phrase.
6
The notational practice shown here is one that has become somewhat standard for drumset. Those instruments controlled by the foot are notated stems down. All the other activity is combined into one composite rhythm with the stems up. It is useful to give a staff key before the actual music, and also to indicate the name of an instrument as it enters. 
This first passage is a composed excerpt, imitating a rock phrase. In this performance a crash cymbal substitutes for a splash cymbal.
13
The notational practice shown here is one that has become somewhat standard for drumset. Those instruments controlled by the foot are notated stems down. All the other activity is combined into one composite rhythm with the stems up. It is useful to give a staff key before the actual music, and also to indicate the name of an instrument as it enters. 
This passage is a transcription of an improvised rock beat.
In this performance a crash cymbal substitutes for a splash cymbal.



D  
 R U M S E T  -  S W I N G
video/drums6.flv 
notes/drums6.swf 
0
The notational practice shown here is one that has become somewhat standard for drumset. Those instruments controlled by the foot are notated stems down. All the other activity is combined into one composite rhythm with the stems up. It is useful to give a staff key before the actual music, and also to indicate the name of an instrument as it enters. 
This passage is a transcription of an improvised swing pattern. In performance, all dotted rhythms are swung -- \"quantized\" to the nearest triplet eighth-note.
4
The notational practice shown here is one that has become somewhat standard for drumset. Those instruments controlled by the foot are notated stems down. All the other activity is combined into one composite rhythm with the stems up. It is useful to give a staff key before the actual music, and also to indicate the name of an instrument as it enters. 
This passage is a transcription of an improvised swing pattern. In performance, all dotted rhythms are swung -- \"quantized\" to the nearest triplet eighth-note.
8
The notational practice shown here is one that has become somewhat standard for drumset. Those instruments controlled by the foot are notated stems down. All the other activity is combined into one composite rhythm with the stems up. It is useful to give a staff key before the actual music, and also to indicate the name of an instrument as it enters. 
This passage is a transcription of an improvised swing pattern. In performance, all dotted rhythms are swung -- \"quantized\" to the nearest triplet eighth-note.
11
The notational practice shown here is one that has become somewhat standard for drumset. Those instruments controlled by the foot are notated stems down. All the other activity is combined into one composite rhythm with the stems up. It is useful to give a staff key before the actual music, and also to indicate the name of an instrument as it enters. 
In this performance a crash cymbal substitutes for a splash cymbal.

