

L  
 O G   D R U M   &   T E M P L E   B L O C K S
video/woods1.flv
notes/woods1.swf
0
Performer: Eric Guinivan
The log drum is also known as the \"slit drum\" and the \"wood drum.\" Its standard construction is a wooden box with the top cut to create two tongues, which sound two different pitches when struck. Wood drums are found in a variety of sizes, and can be paired to create 4 distinct pitches, as in this demonstration. Medium yarn mallets will create the fullest sound.
7
 Eric Guinivan
The log drum is also known as the \"slit drum\" and the \"wood drum.\" Its standard construction is a wooden box with the top cut to create two tongues, which sound two different pitches when struck. Wood drums are found in a variety of sizes, and can be paired to create 4 distinct pitches, as in this demonstration. Hard rubber mallets emphasized the \"wooden\" quality of the drum.
14
When wood is used on wood, the sound of stick itself becomes an important component of the sound, which can be modulated by switching from the heavy, rounded handles to light, pointed tips.
22
Striking the drums on the sides may create a drier, higher sound, although this sound may not be resonant on some instruments.
29
This passage displays a combination of the 3 pitches available on each drum.
40
Temple blocks (when compared with wood blocks) have a deeper more resonant sound, particularly when played with yarn mallets. They are usually used as a group of 5 semi-indefinite pitches.
51
Temple blocks (when compared with wood blocks) have a deeper more resonant sound, particularly when played with yarn mallets. They are usually used as a group of 5 semi-indefinite pitches.
58
Temple blocks (when compared with wood blocks) have a deeper more resonant sound, particularly when played with yarn mallets. They are usually used as a group of 5 semi-indefinite pitches.



W  
 O O D    B L O C K S,   C L A V E S  &  C A S T A N E T S
video/woods2.flv
notes/woods2.swf		
0
Wood blocks are slightly drier and brighter than temple blocks, and more indefinite in pitch.
15
Wood blocks are slightly drier and brighter than temple blocks, and more indefinite in pitch.
25
Claves -- two pitches of wood struck together -- have a very bright and incisive sound. They can project clearly even when played quietly.
36
Castanets used in a percussion section differ in the way they are constructed and played from the traditional folk instruments. The construction shown here allows for detailed rhythmic articulation and convincing rolls. Although two castanets are traditionally employed, the rhythm is generally written as a single line.
41
Castanets used in a percussion section differ in the way they are constructed and played from the traditional folk instruments. The construction shown here allows for detailed rhythmic articulation and convincing rolls. Although two castanets are traditionally employed, the rhythm is generally written as a single line.



W  
 H I S T L E S   &   O T H E R S
video/woods3.flv
notes/woods3.swf
0
The vibraslap is effective when struck once to color an attack.
4
The ratchet is capable of articulating rhythms as well providing a sustained noise.
7
The guiro can produce long or short strokes, providing a distinctive rhythmic personality.
15
Shakers of many sizes and materials are available, and can provide a nuanced variety of articulations.
21
Clay flower pots can be found in many sizes, and provide an interesting alternative to woods and metals.
31
Clay flower pots can be found in many sizes, and provide an interesting alternative to woods and metals.
39
Most percussion inventories are well stocked with whistles and sirens.
44
Most percussion inventories are well stocked with whistles and sirens.
48
Most percussion inventories are well stocked with whistles and sirens.
55
Most percussion inventories are well stocked with whistles and sirens.


